so I call the TP combination testan and
glp1 the mo the closest thing to a
fountain of youth that we've ever
had welcome back to the DRT and hormone
optimization YouTube channel and we have
back with us as a guest Dr Rudy eberwine
welcome back Rudy Hey Stephen always a
pleasure to be here great seeing you
nice to have you so today we're going to
start with uh talk about trt and gp1
what news about this combination um so
this is I'm going to tell you my
favorite tool when it comes to
optimization optimization of my
patient's Health um you know as a
anti-aging physician and optimization
physician we're always trying to see
what tools can we use to optimize
metabolic health because we know that
metabolic disease is the main driver of
the chronic illness epidemic that we'll
see not only in the US but all over the
world but I think the US is the
epicenter of metabolic disease so there
was a recent study that showed that 93%
of Americans suffer from some kind of
cardiometabolic dysfunction
93% if you try to go with metabolic
disease you can bring the that to maybe
two-thirds of Americans and let me go
over some scary statistics With You
Stephen about 40 42% of Americans are
obese two out of three Americans are
either overweight or obese one out of
five um Americans have diabetes or
pre-diabetes or insulin resistance
cancer rates are saring mostly in the
younger population less than 50 heart
disease Remains the number one killer we
have almost 700,000 deaths annually in
heart disease our population is getting
fatter and sicker
despite the available
information that we tell patients you
should eat less and exercise right so
this is what we've always had we I I've
I've studied nutrition and food Sciences
as my undergrad major I've had my weight
loss clinic for the past 20 years
actually this year is 20 years and I've
been screaming at the top of my lungs to
all my patients eat better and exercise
all of the experts are saying the same
thing but what's happened over the past
20 to 40 years we've had an increase a
saring increase in obesity and obesity
related diseases so clearly what we're
doing is not working so enter gp1
medications and what's interesting we've
had this talk before Stephen OIC
semaglutide was FD approved in 2018 and
that's when it entered GP once entered
consciousness of the world they thought
that only semaglutide in 2018 that's
when we had gp1s I've been using gp1
medication since 2005 since they were
first FDA approved because they were
first FDA approved for diabetes they did
not have great success on weight loss
back then so the first one was exenatide
so just as to give people the context on
that gp1s are not a new treatment just
the OIC and mount jaia starting in 2018
have become more effective so now let's
go back to the metabolic crisis that's
affecting our world clearly the status
quo is not working so we needed new
tools and we've talked many times on the
podcast how amazing those peptides
because remember gp1 is a peptide and
it's truly revolutionizing Health Care
revolutionizing metabolic disease and
treatment because we've never had
anything that is as effective at helping
people change their relationship with
food be able to get free of the food
addiction that is pling plaguing 70% of
our population so I've used
gp1s without any shame and without any
issues on my patients who need it
because I've seen the results and the
studies are phenomenal on the amount of
weight loss the insulin resistance that
improves on a decreasing of inflammation
all of those issues so grp1 is one of my
main Tools in my toolbox for
optimization of metabolic disease but
there is no questions that when you lose
weight by any way but even more with
glp1 you can see decreasing lean MUSC
muscle mass and Steve what I like with
me and you we are muscle Centric
Physicians we we believe in muscles and
keeping muscle mass and we've been doing
this for years and even when I was in
med school and in nutrition school I
never understood the importance of
muscle mass and now we know that muscle
lean muscle mass is the most important
currency for wellness and Longevity the
more muscle mass you have as you grow
older the better you will age less risk
of chronic disease because again lean
muscle mass helps decrease insulin
resistance it doesn't just look good
when you take off your shirt it's really
important so what happens as we age or
as we suffer from metabolic disease I
call it the double wamy of inflammaging
increase body fat increased belly fat
and sopia decreasing lean muscle mass
this is what happens as we age or as
somebody's overweight and doesn't
exercise you you see increased belly fat
lower muscle mass and that is a recipe
for disaster so what is the best regimen
to combat this we said already glp1 to
help decrease belly fat visual adapost
tissue overall weight but now combining
it with testosterone to help increase
muscle mass and increase energy and
vitality the combination of testosterone
and grp1 to me is the closest thing to a
fountain of youth that we've ever had
because it addresses those two
components of
inflammaging increase vat visal adapost
tissue and decrease muscle mass
sarcopenia if you can address those two
issues you will have a better metabolic
meure so for me U you know interestingly
I'm in Miami we eat rice and beans in
Miami and rice and beans is a staple
over the world why because when you eat
rice it has amino acids but it doesn't
have all of them when you combine rice
Plus means it provides you the eight
essential amino acids so it's a complete
meal so I see testostrone and gp1 as the
rice and beans of Wellness because those
two complete each other for example and
you see that I have a lot of patients
who are on trt but they still overweight
they have muscle mass but they have a
lot of visual fat or they are overweight
they can't lose the weight adding glp1
to trt is a
lifechanging um therapy because now you
can really help decrease the fat
decrease the weight decrease the body
the visual adpost tissue while
maintaining or increasing lean muscle
mass and the opposite is true a lot of
my patients who've had great success on
glp1 they look good but they start
having that ccop pinic look where you
see the muscles are going away about 45
p% of patients who have insulin
resistance also have some kind of
endogen resistance or Androgen
insufficiency so would it be amazing
that now that we've realized how
important lean muscle masses that we
have testosterone as a prescription to
increase your muscle right would it be
amazing as doctors that we can say h i
see that you're aging Stephen I see that
you're losing your muscle I'm going to
prescribe you testosterone because we'll
be able to build lean muscle mass and we
know that is the most important thing we
can do for your wellness and your
longevity so the big question is always
oh you're going to prescribe too much
testosterone how safe is testosterone
well which recently had the Traverse
trial that followed almost 7,000 men
over 5 years that showed the safety of
testosterone and then me and you we've
been seeing patients um for 20 30 plus
years on testosterone therapy and it is
a win-win not only do those patients
look better feel better but their health
is also improving so I call the tlip
combination teston and glp1 the mo the
closest thing to a fountain of youth
that we've ever had and any providers
who are interested in really helping
patients with metabolic disease should
know about that combination and I'm
going to always put a caveat in this
this doesn't replace good diet this
doesn't replace good nutrition exercise
and sleep optimization the three the
four pillars of Health remain nutrition
exercise sleep and Stress Management you
cannot get away from this however many
people who know this just cannot
sometimes CH change their nutrition we
see that many patients who come to see
me will tell me Doc I know exactly what
I should eat and what what I should not
eat I could write a diet book I can go
chat GPT and give me a 14-day diet I
know what I should do I just cannot do
it day after day I'm stressed um the
food tastes too good so it's it's
microfood addictions because the food
that we nowadays is engineered to make
us addicted to it did you know that in
the United States 70% of our calories
come from ultr processed foods those are
engineered foods that we cannot resist
our system was not made to resist that
it's not natural food so the big the big
um criticism I get from my colleagues is
they tell me Rudy you pay too much
attention to the glp1 we need to change
the food source we need to make our food
healthy
and I agree I I agree 100% And I'm
fighting for this and now I'm excited to
see that in the US we're talking about
this right we have the make America
healthy again movement with RFK Jr
that's finally bringing to light things
I've been talking about for the past 20
years and we need to change our food
system but let's be realistic how
quickly do we think is that going to
change there's too much money riding on
this too many lobbyists I optimistic but
I don't see things changing quickly so
for the doctors who say that don't use
dp1 just tell your patient to eat less
eat organic and exercise more I wish all
my patients could like this and for my
patients who can what is it maybe 20%
30% of my patient who can do diet
behavior modification exercise and
maintain their weight good for you if
you can do it without using any hormones
any supplements I applaud you and I want
you to keep doing this however for the
other 70% of patients or overweight or
obese the other 93% of patients with
metabolic disease we need to realize we
need tools now I cannot wait for the
government or big foods to change the
food source to become healthy so I
believe in the Maha make America healthy
again but my biggest point is Mya I want
to make you healthy again on you have
that power and when I can give you tools
like glp1 that make you decrease your
addiction to those foods I can give you
testosterone that helps you regain
Vitality Health Energy wants you to live
life again now I make you healthy again
and you can make better choices and the
way we change the collective is by
changing the individual so I'm not going
to sit down I consider myself a foot
soldier in that war against against
metabolic disease we need generals like
RFK Jr and those guys who are going
after the Senate and in the government
to try to change that but it's not going
to change overnight we need food
Soldiers with effective tools to help us
deal with the disease right now